what should I do to enhance my brain
function right now and I can't Define
that I don't know if that means I need
to be creative I don't know if that
means I need to have more you know
reaction time
what like where would you start with
that individual in terms
of what you said at the beginning I you
should make your own Baseline test like
what should I be thinking about and are
there some tactics where you say okay I
need all the information I would really
need all but maybe two or three things
here that start off that generally work
pretty well so so generally i' think
about when something like that comes to
me and they say I'm healthy my brain
works great I'm I'd like to improve it
as much as I can or maintain it for as
long as possible the first thing is just
to make sure if that first statement is
true and the easiest way to do that is
with some simple blood tests you know
determine some like nutritional status
becomes really critical for the brain we
can um we can deal with poor nutritional
status and the brain works just fine
early in life but if you're trying to
you know maximize everything we know uh
vitamin D iron status magnesium uh B
vitamins Omega-3s some of these and
glucose glucose regulation or at least
just making sure you don't have
pre-diabetes you know some of the basics
I would just make sure that all of that
is sort of buttoned up and that's and
that's easy to address would you mainly
say those are energy metabolism markers
as long as your energy metabolisms fine
you're probably okay there's an
interesting thing about energy
metabolism in the brain and as it
relates to brain structure as well which
is that it kind of follows a U-shaped
curve so at low levels of energy
availability we start to lose brain
structure and brain function just
because we don't have the energy to
support it and then we see a very clear
energy toxicity effect as well so if we
have you know pre-diabetes
diabetes um lipid disregulation you all
the markers of energy toxicity which are
very very common right 2third if not
more adults in the US have some version
of that then you start to see a decline
in cive function and brain volume as
well so yes energy regulation is really
important but some of those nutrients
have their own um effects in terms of
brain structure as well so if you think
about the relationship between B
vitamins and Omega-3s this has been
shown again and again and again that
they interact so if you have good status
of one but not the other you see no
effect and vice versa and this is where
we've had trials that say we give
Omega-3s but they don't work or we give
B vitamins but they don't work but they
haven't taking the the other into
account and it makes perfect sense
because if you want DHA the long chain
omega3 fatty acid to sit in the sinapse
where you want it you know to help
communication between two neurons it
needs to first get into the brain and
that requires usually healthy uh instant
sensitivity in energy regulation and
then it needs to go down the path of
being attached to some kind of
phospholipid right so choline or Serene
or
ethanolamine uh so you need that to be
available and then you need methylation
to work so these things get attached
together that's where the B Vis become
important so some of these things are
directly structural uh as well as being
you know functional thinking about
energy M and mitochondria I don't want
to lose the plot I'll come back to our
Avatar here in a second I have many
follow-ups to that I'll I'll ask just
one though I don't think people would
have assumed you can get a reasonable
assessment of shortterm immediate acute
cognitive function from
blood so uh right now you probably can't
um you and I are in the process of uh
developing what should be a fairly
simple uh blood test that relates
directly to cognitive function dementia
risk also mortality risk but like I said
critically cognitive function right now
it's not going to be perfect but it does
relate generally to nutritional status
and energy status which which makes
perfect sense so on top of that I think
you could um you know really button up
the details with making sure that all
you have all your nutrient ducts uh in a
row but in reality if you were going to
try at the population level at least try
and predict some of these cognitive
function you could see or if they have
pre-diabetes or any kind of um nutrient
deficiency they're going to have lower
cognitive function and there's there's
you know dozens hundreds of studies that
show that do they need to necessarily be
at a technical deficiency there or if
they're you know say bottom 10th
percentile they should pay attention do
we have any insights into where those
cut offs start to lie for these metrics
yeah it it
probably you're you're right that in
general what we consider to be a a
deficiency nowadays is usually you're
below the normal range right you're in
the bottom 2.5% of some nutrient marker
and right you're like you're going to
have some your day-to-day cognitive
function is not your ma your main issue
right there's going to be even bigger
problems than that but there are some
cut offs for for all of these things uh
well in in general say blood sugar
regulation you want to make sure that
normal fasting blood sugar not
pre-diabetic beyond that there's
probably not that much benefit from from
from being lower than that but something
like homine as a marker of methylation
status um generally if you went to a lab
the normal range is 13 15 um five to
five to like bottom end five high end 13
14 15 and most people will say you sort
of like Target below 15 in terms of
cognitive function it probably needs to
be less than 11 uh some people would go
a little bit lower than that for things
like cardiovascular disease risk um but
then uh similarly for omega-3 fatty
acids if you do something like the
omega-3 index you probably want to be
like ideally over 6% maybe close to 8%
or higher um and that like I said those
those two things interact yeah I would
say that in our
experience if you are above 9 to 10 for
home assisting we're we're looking very
seriously at other things yeah and an
Omega you'd be surprised how many are
under five yeah like very very very very
commonly this is why you see in those
folks a little bit of basic multivitamin
and omega-3 support and all of a sudden
the brain fog is gone the decline like
it it just disappears from these people
really quickly which is is really of no
surprise so um coming back to us then we
check those blood markers uh then what
for that
so then you can make sure that the other
lifestyle factors are sort of all in a
row and when we think about long-term
cognitive function there's kind of a a
framework for thinking about
that so sleep and all these other things
stress mitigation um I'd I'd definitely
you know look at all these other
lifestyle factors but if you're thinking
about enhancing cognitive function like
I said earlier I think stimulus is
really the most important thing your
avatar probably has quite a cognitively
stimulating job which we know uh
increases long-term cognitive function
and decreases the risk of dementia
longterm so then I would think about a a
lifelong plan of ongoing broad cognitive
stimuli so if he's never played a
musical instrument he learns to play a
musical instrument if he um all his
exercise is in the gym and it's uni
modal then he picks up an open skill
sport he goes to play pickle ball or
learns to skateball God forbid no more
people playing pickle ball don't do that
Tommy um if he uh has never spoken
another language then he then he learns
a language um some of these things
it's interesting when you look across
the literature the one activity that
probably takes a lot of these boxes and
seems to really support cognitive
function as well as mental health is
dancing and because that brings in play
like it's it's an open skill there's
music it's social um so he so dance
class with his partner right would be a
great a great way to sort of integrate a
bunch of these things together if you
enjoyed this clip you can watch the full
episode by clicking here